### ARNAB KUMAR PAUL

#### Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science at Virginia Tech

@ akpaul [at] vt [dot] eduBlacksburg, VA, U.S.A.

+1 (540) 998 - 1480
 Distributed Systems and Storage Laboratory, Virginia Tech
 https://arnabkrpaul.github.io/
 in arnabkrpaul



### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### **Graduate Research Intern**

Cray Inc.

Mentor: Cory Spitz, Nathan Rutman (Cray), and Scott White (LANL)

🛗 Jun. 2019 - Aug. 2019

**♀** Los Alamos, NM, U.S.A.

• Scalable metadata indexing for large scale distributed file systems.

**Graduate Student Summer Intern (Computation Scholar)** 

**Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory** 

Advisor: Dr. Kathryn Mohror

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

♀ Livermore, CA, U.S.A.

- Analyze the metadata and job statistics of HPC I/O workloads.
- Build predictive models of I/O workloads based on the time series server data.

**Graduate Student Summer Intern (Research Aide)** 

**Argonne National Laboratory** 

Advisor: Dr. Ian Foster

May 2017 - Aug. 2017

• Built a scalable monitoring solution for arbitrary file systems.

Ph.D. Student @ Virginia Tech

**Distributed Systems and Storage Laboratory** 

Advisor: Dr. Ali R. Butt

Aug. 2015 - PRESENT

♥ Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, U.S.A.

- Optimizing containers in HPC storage systems.
- Load balancing in large scale storage systems, such as Lustre.
- Auto-tuning of parallelism in Spark

Masters Student @ National Institute of Technology, Rourkela Information Security and Data Communication Laboratory

Advisor: Dr. Bibhudatta Sahoo

May 2014 - May 2015

NIT Rourkela, Odisha, India

• Dynamic virtual machine placement in cloud computing.

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor (Virginia Tech) Aug. 2019 - Jan. 2020

• CS 2505: Intro Computer Organization - Fall 2019

Graduate Teaching Assistant (Virginia Tech) Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2019

- CS 3214: Operating Systems Spring 2019
- CS 5584: Network Security Fall 2018
- CS 3114: Data Structures and Algorithms *Spring 2018*
- CS 2506: Computer Org II Fall 2017
- CS 2114: Software Design and Data Structures - Fall 2016, Spring 2017
- CS 1054: Introduction to Programming in Java Fall 2015, Spring 2016

Graduate Teaching Assistant (NIT Rourkela) Aug. 2014 - May 2015

• CS 171: Computing Lab - Autumn 2014, Spring 2015

• CS 670: Data Mining Lab - Spring 2015

### LIFE PHILOSOPHY

"Your best teacher is your last mistake." - Dr. A. P. J. Abdul Kalam

### RESEARCH STATEMENT

I am a fifth year Ph.D. candidate in the Department of Computer Science at Virginia Tech. I work in the Distributed Systems and Storage Laboratory headed by Dr. Ali R. Butt. My research interests include cloud computing, distributed systems, distributed file systems and big data APIs.

#### **EDUCATION**

### Ph.D. in Computer Science

Virginia Tech

- Advisor: Dr. Ali R. Butt
- GPA: 4.0/4.0

## M.S. in Computer Science & Applications Virginia Tech

## Aug. 2015 - May 2018

• GPA: 3.85/4.0

## M.Tech. in Computer Science & Engineering National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

## Aug. 2013 - May 2015

- Specialization: Software Engineering
- Advisor: Dr. Bibhudatta Sahoo
- GPA: 9.56/10.0

## B.Tech. in Computer Science & Engineering West Bengal University of Technology

🛗 Aug. 2009 - May 2013

• GPA: 9.02/10.0

### **SKILLS**

Lustre File System Apache Spark Containers **Edge Computing** IoT C++ **JAVA** C# Pvthon **SCALA** MySQL HTML **CSS** UNIX git svn latex gnuplot

### MENTORING EXPERIENCE

- Arpit Goyal MS, Virginia Tech, 2016 17
- Subil Abraham MS, Virginia Tech, 2019 20
- Debasmita Biswas MS, Virginia Tech, 2020 -
- Redwan Ibne Seraj Khan PhD, Virginia Tech, 2019 -

### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

#### Book Chapters

• Paul, Arnab Kumar and Bibhudatta Sahoo (2017). *Dynamic virtual machine placement in cloud computing*. IGI Global, pp. 136–167.

### Conference & Workshop Proceedings

- Paul, Arnab K, Brian Wang, et al. (2020). "Efficient Metadata Indexing for HPC Storage Systems". In: 20th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Cluster, Cloud and Internet Computing (CCGrid).
- Paul, Arnab K, Ryan Chard, et al. (2019). "FSMonitor: Scalable File System Monitoring for Arbitrary Storage Systems". In: 2019 IEEE Cluster. IEEE.
- Paul, Arnab K, Olaf Faaland, Adam Moody, Elsa Gonsiorowski, Kathryn Mohror, and Ali Butt (2019). "Understanding HPC Application I/O Behavior Using System Level Statistics". In: Poster - SC 2019.
- Paul, Arnab K, Olaf Faaland, Adam Moody, Elsa Gonsiorowski, Kathryn Mohror, and Ali R Butt (2019). "Improving I/O Performance of HPC Application Using Intra-Job Scheduling". In: Work-In-Progress in Proceedings of the 4th Joint International Workshop on Parallel Data Storage & Data Intensive Scalable Computing Systems (PDSW-DISC'19) in conjunction with SC'19.
- Sim, Hyogi et al. (2019). "Cslim: Automated Extraction of IoT Functionalities from Legacy C Codebases". In: 2019 8th International Workshop on Computing and Networking for IoT and Beyond (ComNet-IoT), Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking. ACM, pp. 421–426.
- Wadhwa, Bharti et al. (2019). "Resource Contention Aware Load Balancing for Large-Scale Parallel File Systems". In: 2019 33rd IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS).
- Paul, Arnab K, Arpit Goyal, et al. (2017). "I/O load balancing for big data hpc applications". In: 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data). IEEE, pp. 233–242.
- Paul, Arnab K, Steven Tuecke, et al. (2017). "Toward scalable monitoring on large-scale storage for software defined cyberinfrastructure". In: Proceedings of the 2nd Joint International Workshop on Parallel Data Storage & Data Intensive Scalable Computing Systems. ACM, pp. 49–54.
- Paul, Arnab Kumar, Wenjie Zhuang, et al. (2016). "Chopper: Optimizing data partitioning for in-memory data analytics frameworks". In: 2016 IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing (CLUSTER). IEEE, pp. 110–119.
- Datta, Arjun and Arnab Kumar Paul (2014). "Online compiler as a cloud service". In: 2014 International Conference on Advanced Communication Control and Computing Technologies (ICACCCT). IEEE, pp. 1783–1786.
- Paul, Arnab Kumar, Sourav Kanti Addya, et al. (2014). "Application of greedy algorithms to virtual machine distribution across data centers". In: 11<sup>th</sup> IEEE India Conference INDICON 2014, Emerging Trends and Innovation of Technology. IEEE, pp. 1–6.

### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

2020

- TBitshares Fellowship by CS @ VT
- Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT

2019

- Member of Association for India's Development
- ▲ Member of CS Graduate Council @ VT

  ☐ Travel Grant IEEE Cluster '19
- Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT
- Student Volunteer, SC '19

2018

- P Bitshares Fellowship by CS @ VT
- Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT
- Student Volunteer, SCiNet @ SC '18

2017

President of Bengali Students' Ass. @ VT Travel Grant IEEE BigData '17

2016

Travel Grant IEEE Cluster '16

Student Volunteer, SC '16

2015

# Gold Medalist, CS @ NITRKL

# PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

PC Member

**■** ICDCS 2020

Reviewer

- IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems - 2019, 2020
- Cluster Computing Journal 2019, 2020
- ASTESJ Journal 2018
- **I** IJGHPC Journal 2018, 2019, 2020
- AUTOSOFT Journal 2018
- MGS Journal 2017

**External Reviewer** 

- **■** IEEE TSC Journal '18
- © BigData '17/'18, Cluster '17/'18, ECOOP '20, HPDC '17/'18/'20, IC2E '17, ICCD '19, ICDCS '17/'18/'19, ICS '17/'18, IPDPS '18/'19/'20

### **REFEREES**

Dr. Ali R. Butt

- @ butta@cs.vt.edu